A difficult conversation can be a great way
to build your interpersonal skills.
Yes, hear me out.
What if you didn't allow potentially difficult conversations to drain you,
and instead, used them as a means
to cultivate strong relationships?
In the face of a difficult conversation,
you may feel as if you're standing at a doorstep.
It may be that you're looking at a closed door in front of you,
fearing what you may encounter on the other side.
So you're just standing there paralyzed,
and unwilling to open the mysterious door.
Or it may be that you are ready to open the door,
but you are dreading it.
Your mindset is fixed, and you believe
that nothing good can come out of the conversation.
In either case, you may make up stories about the other person.
Perhaps you don't appreciate some of their characteristics,
and you blame them for making you feel uneasy.
Or you may make up stories about yourself.
For example, thinking this will ruin your already shaky relationship,
or that you'll end up with a bad reputation.
You may start feeling guilt or shame,
or experience physical symptoms, like a racing heart or nausea.
Other times you may rationalize it:
“It isn't a good time, I'm too busy for this.”
All the while, the door to a more resilient
and productive relationship remains shut.
Here's a tip. Be curious.
Open the door with a resilient mindset and with attention,
vulnerability, empathy, and compassion.
Because even a potentially difficult conversation is actually an opportunity
to build a stronger, more meaningful relationship.
Some very common examples of difficult conversations are
tough performance dialogues, feedback conversations, and team discussions.
It can be tempting to leave the doors to those conversations closed.